Welcome to another edition of the Giants
Total Access brought to you by Citizens,
the official bank of the Giants. I am
John Schmelk. Very excited to welcome
back to the show for a second time. He
joined us back, I think, early
September, late August to preview the
season. We said we'd join up again
before the draft, and here he is, former
NFL general manager Ran Carthon. Ran,
it's good to talk to you, man. How are
you? Man, I'm good, man. Like we were
just talking about off air, feeling old.
Um went out of town one day this week,
came back with a cold. Weak immune
system. It's just life is life-ing.
>> [laughter]
>> Dude, I've been dealing with like hip
bursitis for like 6 weeks, and I haven't
been able to play basketball. It's been
absolutely killing me, but it's just old
man problems. That's pretty much what it
is. Yeah, absolutely, 100%. But hey, I
wouldn't have it any other way.
Glad I'm above ground having these
problems than than than the other side
of it. Yeah, you're absolutely right.
And look, this is the fun type of year,
right? For for people like you, this is
where you guys, you know,
run your craft, make your money. So, you
have the Giants here, you kind of go
through free agency. I'm going to start
big picture first, right? You go through
free agency, you try to fill as many
holes as you can so you're not trapped
in terms of what you want to do in the
draft. But a lot of these Giants
signings, at least some of them, were
one-year deals, like uh Greg Newsome
corner, Dono Mooney, Calvin Austin at
wide receiver. Um they haven't gotten a
guy that you would think is going to be
their starting right guard yet. When you
think about guys on one-year deals, and
then you start thinking about the draft,
do they even kind of enter your thought
process, Ran, in terms of when you
assess your needs, or is drafting a guy
such a long-term proposition, you almost
act like those one-year guys almost
aren't even here? You know what I mean?
Yeah, no, the one-year guys are, you
know, in most cases, uh they're bridges,
right? Because you can't just assume,
well, we'll get this guy in the draft,
right? You don't know how the draft is
going to fall, you don't know what moves
are going to be made around you that
will prevent you from getting a guy you
covet. You don't I mean, obviously, the
folks within the Giants front office, uh
they're doing their homework, they have
their sources, they have their resources
to find out information, but you can't
lean on that. And so, when an
opportunity presents itself for you to
be able to get a bridge,
specifically a player you know or you've
coached or coached against that you
think can help you,
um and help establish a new way cuz it's
it's different from being a program
where the head coach has been around a
long time versus a new head coach coming
in um that wants to implement implement
his way of doing things,
and you need purveyors of your message.
You need guys that can carry your
message throughout the locker room and
be the epitome of what you want the
Giants program to be moving forward. So,
those one-year deals just kind of help
you bridge the gap just in case, you
know, you're not able to address those
positions via the draft.
>> I think that makes sense. When you look
when you assess your needs as a general
manager when you go into a draft, Ran,
how much do you look 2 years down the
road? This is a thing I did on our Big
Blue Kickoff Live show last week and
say, all right, well, I'm going to have
a hole at this position in 2027 and this
spot and this spot, I'm worried about
that. Just an example, the Giants right
now have don't have a guard or a center
under contract for the 2027 season. I
might think that's a problem. How much
are you looking 2 years down the road
and not just at this year when you're
thinking about who you're going to
draft? Yeah, I always say you got to
have one foot in the current year and
and one and your eyes out in the in the
coming years, right? Because it's all
it's forecasting. You got to see the
future to a degree or understand what's
coming in the future. How hard is it
going to be to re-sign Kayvon Thibodeaux
after this year with the amount of money
that that position is getting and
whether you feel like him or any other
pass rusher is worth the money they're
getting.
That's the market. It's like the housing
market, you know, you may not want to
pay those prices for a home in a
specific neighborhood, but if you want
to live in that neighborhood, that's the
price you're going to have to pay. And
so, for the Giants, right, especially at
the edge rush position, those are what I
call first world problems.
You know, you have three legitimate
guys, three guys that we know can play
in the league, that can get after the
quarterback. And so, now you put
yourself in a position where if you
don't want to pay Thibodeaux
after a couple years, and you know you
have Abdul Carter.
And someone that you believe that can be
a solid replacement for Thibodeaux or or
Brian Burns, for that matter. However
they decide to do it within their
organization. But, you know, to answer
your question, you have you have to
have, you know, your foot in 2026 and
this cycle of player acquisition, but
with your eyes to 27 and 28. Now, the
other thing too, Ran, is that free
agency is not over, right? The first
wave is over, you could argue the second
wave is over, but there's still a bunch
of guys, mostly veterans, that are still
out there. You know, maybe these guys
are waiting for more money to come your
way. Maybe these guys just don't want to
do the off-season program, and they're
happy to, you know, sign in July and
show up for training camp. Um how much
do you consider the conversations you
might have had as a general manager with
some of the free agents that are still
available. And I'm thinking, let's say
for say example, Greg Van Roten for the
Giants. He was a starter the last 2
years at right guard, he's still a free
agent. He signed late in the process his
first year here. When you're thinking
about what you have to do in the draft
based on needs, and maybe what free
agents you think you can still get in
the building even after the draft? You
get to May, June, and July, things like
that. Yeah, I mean, you're looking at
that. You're still monitoring, you're
having, you know, whether if you're the
Giants, whether it's, you know, Brandon
Brown or
Dennis Hickey or whomever, Tim McDonal,
those guys are still staying in touch
with these agents of the free agents
that are out there. They're kind of
keeping their eyes and their ears to the
street, understanding what the market
is, how much of the money is drying up
because it's
if you're if you're a free agent and
you're still on the street because
you're holding out with the hopes of
having more money, you're just a bad
business person, right? [laughter]
Because the money's
the money's drying up, and then now
teams are going to have to I mean, it's
already budgeted for, but you got to
budget for your draft picks, right? And
who who knows what may happen on draft
night. You may acquire more picks, which
now, you know, adds to that budget that
you've allocated for being able to sign
the draft picks. And you got to have
operating expenses
heading into the season. And so, that
money is drying up.
But I think, you know, for let's use the
example you said Greg Van Roten.
I'm sure they've been talking to his,
you know, his people. And again, new
regime. So, you know, the Greg Van Roten
fit may not at necessarily fit, but I'm
sure it does. And so, the conversation
is probably being had with his team just
in terms of, hey, we're still
interested, what do you guys have? You
know, if he wants to take his time, you
know, there may be some other things
that we're not, you know, privy to
that may be going on. But you're having
those conversations, you're keeping your
ears and your eyes open to it. I know
for myself, um I think it was, yeah, my
first year
in the chair,
um signed DeAndre Hopkins late in in the
process.
Um and I think but I think he got
released. I think he had a post-June 1
designation.
But it was all things that we had
understood what were going on, still
understanding there are some cap
casualties who may be cut. Um just
again, with the understanding of what's
to come, that forecasting I was talking
about previous. Yeah, exactly. And if
not Van Roten, then, you know, Daniel
Fallale was someone that was with
Harbaugh. Kevin Zeitler was someone that
was with Harbaugh, right? And one of
those guys at guard that you think can
kind of bring in and and play that spot
if you don't end up drafting um one of
those players. All right, let's talk
about the draft process now. As a
general manager, what did you get out of
this part of the process, where you're
going to pro days, you're seeing guys
work out, you're doing the 30 visits?
What are you trying to achieve in this,
you know, last run-up of 3-4 weeks
before the draft? Well, I'll be honest
with you, I always call this is um
I call the earlier part of process
everyone being nosy, right? It's because
everyone's trying to figure out what
what the next person is doing, who likes
who, who's showing up where.
So, you know, for me, pro day,
uh for some of the guys that I may not
have been able to see move around live,
I would like to see them move around
live.
Uh again, for me, it's I take a
different approach to it, um
cuz I lean heavily on the tape and what
the tape has shown me over the last
couple of seasons.
But like certain positions,
and I talked about this somewhere I was
on air this week, um like the
quarterback position. You know, I want
to be at the pro day to see how
his teammates respond to him. To see how
people in the building react to him. See
how he engages with people in the
building. Um because to me, that tells
you a lot about the person um and the
human cuz I'm a big believer in that,
being able to get the right type of
person to come into and, you know, and
insert them into not only the
organization, but your city and your
state um because they have to be good
people. Um so, that that type of stuff
is important, but then also,
um again, and and and I have some of the
stuff here in front of me just going
back in my research cuz I was just
recently at the University of Miami's
pro day, where the Giants came out, um
had a large contingency of people there.
Those are some of the things I pay
attention to, as well. I look at the
trends. Like [snorts] um
you know, for example, if
back in the day with the Pittsburgh
Steelers,
if Mike Tomlin, Kevin Colbert, and uh I
want to say Dan Rooney, if they were all
at a pro day,
you knew they were really interested in
a particular player, right? And so,
those are like the little things, those
little type nuggets I'm looking at
and trying to figure out, okay,
I saw [snorts] Joe Schoen, I saw Brandon
Brown, you know, I saw this person, I
saw this person, I saw Dennis Hickey.
I'm like, okay, who are they interested
in?
Right? And give that gives you tips
because now if you're sitting there
within that certain range, then you
know, okay, and they've top-30 visited
this guy, there's a chance that they're
looking here, so we may and it's a need,
so we may have to position ourselves to
move ahead of them if there was a player
that we specifically coveted. But just
in terms of the evaluation process, I
think I think I'd use the combine and
the pro day more so to confirm what I've
seen on tape.
That makes sense.
Um you know, if a guy goes out and he
runs 4-3
then now I could go back to my notes and
say, "Hey man, I thought this guy could
really run on tape." So I'm I'm not wild
and it it just because he runs 4-3
doesn't mean I'm moving him up four
rounds, you know, on on my draft board
just because he ran a specific time. I
lean heavily on the tape and I judge
more so the play speed than the
necessary time speed. When you talk
about play speed and you're right, you
do watch that on tape. How much did you
use and how useful did you find some of
the college GPS data that that that you
guys get now in terms of they give you
actual play speed, some change of
direction stuff sometime. How much did
you use that and how useful was that in
conjunction with the tape and some of
the time stuff at the combine? No, you
use it you know, obviously as a as a
part of it. The greatest example I love
to give is when I was in San Francisco
and we were in the draft process and we
were watching Dre Greenlaw, the
linebacker. And I think at his pro day
he may have ran like 4-7.
And we were like
"I don't know if that time is right.
Like he he plays so much faster
than 4-7." And so you know, we everyone
was stumped, right? Everyone was
stumped. And and it didn't help like Dre
was 5'11,
under 230 and then you run 4-7 you're
like, "Ah, that's kind of a ugly card
that you're looking at on the draft
board."
But then we was like, "Okay, well let's
use our resources. Let's contact you
know, our sources at University of
Arkansas and let's let's get some of
these GPS times." Well, you get the GPS
times and you see that he's reached 20
miles an hour. He's reached 21 miles an
hour. And this was back at a time where
>> [snorts]
>> the GPS times they just gave you that
that one good burst. But now the GPS
times can give you that max speed and
how long they were able to hold that max
speed, which I think is a is a better
indication
of how fast someone is versus that one
quick burst. You don't know what that
burst was.
You don't know if he was in chase mode
because he got beat, you know,
>> [laughter]
>> and he's just just laying it all on the
line and so
you know, it's it's a better indication
now of those
you know, for the speeds, you know,
because again you're watching play
speed. You can understand better
because I mean let's face it, some guys
just can't run a 40.
Right? And that's that's just is what it
is or you have those guys that it's you
don't have pads on
and you've trained for it and you're
just running in a straight line for 40
yards as fast as you can. Well, we all
know and John, you've been around the
game a ton of years.
You know when you're playing on the
actual football field, instincts have a
part into it, right? So if you know you
could be you could run 4-2, but if you
don't know where you're going, you're
not going to move as fast, right? So
so all those things come into account.
But to answer your larger question,
you use the the GPS times to kind of
again confirm what you've seen on tape.
And also you can run really well when
you're in shorts and a t-shirt. When
you're worried about guys hitting you,
you might not be running as fast on the
field either, which is part of the
scenario there as well. Joined by Ryan
Carthona, he's the host with Ryan Wilson
on the with the first pick podcast on
CBS. We thank him for joining us. You
mentioned traits when you talk about Dre
Greenlaw. Did you have thresholds at
each position? How hard and fast were
you with those thresholds in terms of
height, weight, length, stuff like that?
I feel like this draft class there's a
lot of outliers at a lot of different
positions. Like so how did you treat
those traits and kind of what you found
were your thresholds at positions and
and just kind of how you work through
that part of it? Oh yeah, we definitely
had
again, we're we're in the data age now.
And so you have all the historical data
you know, based on your offensive,
defensive, special team systems,
you have specific size size, speed,
length thresholds. One of the cool
things that this whole Shanahan, McVay,
LaFleur tree
specifically with their offenses,
they have well, we we would have
meetings that we call profile meetings,
profile tape meetings where every
position coach would put together a
profile of what they wanted their room
to look like. So if you're a wide
receiver coach, you're going to come in
and you're going to have your
your wide receiver
profile tape meeting. You're going to
have what you want your X to look like,
what you want your Z to look like, what
you want your F. And then they even went
as far as giving us the prototype.
Right? So at the prototype X, Julio
Jones. Prototype Z is you know, Davante
Adams. Prototype F, you know, let's say
Wes Welker or whomever. Whatever it is
that you're wanting
out of those positions and then give us
clips. You get clips of how you know,
when we say, "Hey, double up at the line
of scrimmage." Here's 10 clips of what
we're talking about. You know, when
we're talking about
being able to stack you know, the corner
at the line of scrimmage, here's what
we're talking about. So you get those
tapes and what that what that allows the
it makes the scouts' job easier. Cuz now
you can you can take the guesswork out
of it. You know specifically what fits
in your system. And the cool thing for
you guys is you guys have a new
defensive coordinator in Donard Wilson
who I've worked with at two different
stops. We worked together at the St.
Louis / LA Rams and then we worked
together most previously in Tennessee.
He has that for his defense.
Right? He knows exactly what he wants at
every single position, what it looks
like and can give you the example of
what it looks like. So it's going to
make the scouts' job easier to pull
defensive players that fit Donard's
system. Same thing with the new pass
game coordinator
and obviously worked with him here,
Brian Callahan. Because of his previous
experiences, he knows exactly what he
wants in the quarterback. Now you guys
are in a unique position cuz you already
have a quarterback. Um but you know,
moving forward, what does he want out of
the backup quarterback? What is what are
the traits that he's looking for in
having the next guy behind Jackson Dart?
So that's going to make the scouts' job
easier. And again, you go back I mean,
just take it all the way now to the top
of John Harbaugh. When John Harbaugh
took over as the head coach of the
Baltimore Ravens
the Raven way, if you will, had already
been established. There are only certain
teams in the league where it's the
Baltimore Ravens, it's the Pittsburgh
Steelers. When you say those two
franchises' names
an image of what that player looks like
immediately comes to your head. Right?
And that's what the Giants used to be
back in the day when when it was a
Parcells team, you knew exactly you
know, what a New York Giant looked like.
He was a literal giant. You know what I
mean? And so
I think you guys will get back to that
way where there will be a certain fit
type of certain fit and style of player
that will symbolize what a New York
Giant is. All right, so I guess before
we get to to the Giants make pick at
five then we should probably talk about
what you think this offense and defense
might look like and what they're looking
for, right? You have
you have a lot of experience on defense
with Donard Wilson as you mentioned. I
was going to get that at the end, but I
think we should do it now. What do you
think this defense is going to look
like? What is he looking for? Um and and
in terms of how he wants to fill out the
corner position, the linebacker spot,
just what is going to be the personality
of this defense and what type of players
will he be looking for, do you think?
>> Well, I can tell you the personality of
the defense will be about dogs.
It'll all it'll all be about dogs and
I don't know how much I'll say. You can
beep it out on the edit, but Donard has
an acronym dog, D A W G. A disciplined
with grit.
And that's what you that's what this
defense will look like, a bunch of
disciplined
with grit. And so you're going to see
guys
flying [snorts] around, being violent,
obviously within the rules, you know,
playing to the echo of the whistle and
just initiating contact, right? Not
sitting back waiting on things to
happen, but dictating the tempo
themselves. That's what the defense will
look like.
Um I'm interested to see what the
offense is going to look like. Obviously
with with with Matt Nagy
coming over as the offensive
coordinator.
>> Cuz you got Nagy, you got Roman, you got
Callahan. All of them kind of three
different systems, right? I'm really
curious to see what it looks like. Yeah,
and I'm I'm yeah, I'm I'm obviously real
you know, real curious about that
myself. Just to more so really to see
what the passing game is going to look
like in the concepts. Now again, hey if
we're being realistic, there's only so
many different route combinations that
you can come up with at this point. Um
but it'll be interesting to see how that
all comes together, how Yeah, is it
shotgun? Is it under center? Like I'm I
want to see all that. Yeah, and I I and
I think you will just because of
you know, just Nagy's let's call it West
Coast system background. I think
Callahan has the same
background as does Greg Roman. I think
they've all evolved just based off of
the players that they've had, but I
think all three guys' foundation is the
West Coast
offense. So I think you'll see more of
those concepts just just evolved to a
newer to a newer way of getting there.
Yeah, and I think John Harbaugh is still
going to want to have a you know, the
head coach's personality is going to
come out in this, right? So it's going
to be a physical, run-oriented offense I
think first and foremost, correct? No, I
think so. And I was thinking about that
before we were coming on just in terms
of where the Giants could go with five
because I think they're going to
I mean, we all know the the draft starts
at two.
And I think by the you know, the closer
we get to it, I don't know that I think
that even that pick the will probably
number two pick will come a little bit
more clear.
And so I ultimately do think the wild
card right now is the Arizona Cardinals
and where they'll go, which I think, you
know, and I know we'll get to it here in
a second, but um I think there'll be a
nice little clump of players for the
Giants at five. I think there may be a
perfect world scenario. But then I also
think there'll be a nice clump at five
that they'll be choosing from. Eli, get
in here. If you're lined up here, you
got to go over the middle with it to
score. Great. How do we make that
happen?
I don't know, but Citizens does. [music]
Make sense of your money with Citizens.
Official bank of Eli Manning. Yeah, I
think there will be two. All right,
folks, we'll get to the pick right now,
but don't forget the Giants total
podcast is brought to you by Citizens,
official bank of the Giants for game day
celebrations to your everyday financial
needs. Big Blue fans get the most out of
every moment with Citizens. Learn more
at citizensbank.com/giants.
All right, Raan, so let's talk about it.
Pick number five here.
I don't think we know exactly who's
going to be available, so we'll kind of
talk about a clump of players. Let's
start here. Where does your like kind of
first-tier of top top guys in this class
end? I think I have
I I I'll kind of push Mendoza aside cuz
he's a quarterback, they're separate.
But I think I have three position guys
that I have kind of in my like top top
tier above everybody else. I'm curious
kind of where you have that line drawn,
or maybe four, where you have that line
drawn where you first get that drop off
in this year's draft class. Well, I
think the ultimate drop off uh
let's just say
you know, I don't want to I feel like
the number that first came to my mind is
kind of low.
Uh but I think the the first
>> I mean, look, I have I got Reese,
Styles, Downs, and then kind of Baly's
hovering around there, Bains hovering
around there, and that's kind of what my
first group looks like with the Lane and
Tate kind of hovering as well. It's It
is It isn't a big blue-chip group this
year. It's just not.
>> No, it's it's definitely not. Um but
from you know, from that standpoint, um
you know, I I love Ar'vell Reese. I've
been a Caleb Downs fan for a very very
very long time. He was actually the
first player I evaluated from this
year's draft class, and I did that
probably 2 weeks after last year's draft
just because I had been waiting so long
to be able to watch him and actually
evaluate him.
>> the same thing. That's funny.
But just always been a big fan of his.
Um
but I think as you go, I think there are
certain players that I think um will be
better pros than they were college
players. Uh one player I'm
super duper intrigued by is uh the wide
receiver Chris Braswell out of
Tennessee. Me, too.
And it's unfortunate that Giants fans
have the history with Jalin Hyatt. Um
and they kind of clump uh Chris Braswell
into that. And the hard part for
anybody, I believe, is evaluating these
receivers out of this University of
Tennessee offense
>> because if they're not on the front side
of the route progression, then they're
on the back side just walking off the
line of scrimmage.
It's not because they're lazy or they
don't play hard. It's just what they're
taught, right? And so you don't really
get to see those guys run a variety of
routes, but if you watch the film close
enough or you pour through enough film,
you see all the traits you need to see
out of a guy like Chris Braswell to say
that he can definitely do it. Um coming
into the season, I had Jordan Tyson
ranked as my number one wide receiver um
because I thought you saw him perform
more like a number one wide receiver,
you know, as opposed to Carnell Tate.
Not taking anything away from Carnell
Tate. I think he's just had the luxury
of playing with so many great players
that it allowed him to have a lot of
one-on-one matchups on the back side.
So, um
I think the big talk right now probably
amongst scouts, amongst uh coaching
staffs is is Carnell Tate a legitimate
number one wide receiver. Yeah. Right.
And uh and then how much is
the um hamstring injury concerns going
to affect Jordan Tyson um moving
forward. I think if you're looking at
all things considered and Jordan Tyson
is indeed healthy and the hamstring
issues that he's had aren't an issue, I
think to me he is still the number one
wide receiver in this draft class
because again,
you've seen him play a variety of
positions. He's played outside, he's
played inside, he's played X, he's
played Z, he's played F.
And you knew in crunch time and Arizona
State had a drive, a got to have a
drive, the ball was going to Jordan
Tyson.
And the other team knew it, too, and he
still made plays. Um whereas again, with
a guy like Carnell Tate, you know, he
played opposite of uh
of Jeremiah Smith who got a lot of the,
you know, the coverage looks where
they're rolling double coverage over to
him.
And yet and still Ohio State was still
looking to get the ball to Jeremiah
Smith in those got to have it moments.
So,
um
But yeah, I think this year's draft
class may not have the
the magnitude of blue-chip players um
which you typically want to take in the
top five, the top 10. I don't know that
a lot of draft class come out with 10
blue-chip guys, right? Oh, no,
absolutely not.
But I but I think this year's draft
class in particular, probably once you
get to about the 22 range, I think 22
to let's just broaden it. Let's say it's
from 22 to 50, they're probably all very
similar.
Um and it just becomes your flavor, what
you what you like, what you prefer.
Um but I think you can make an argument
for most of those guys in that top 50 or
the back half of the 50 to you can make
an argument for them to go in the back
half of the first round. No, Raan, I'm
with you 100%. Let's Let's go to Downs.
You mentioned him very quickly because
he did not test, he's not going to test.
He's not big, right? He's just over 200
lb. He's only 6 ft. He's not super long.
So, you know, it's hard to put him in
that Kyle Hamilton, Derwin James class
cuz those guys are big physical freaks,
right? Downs isn't. But like you, you
watch him. I just feel like the way he
can read route combinations, he's always
in the right place. He's dynamite at the
line of scrimmage. He's a great tackler.
Um he's smart, he's versatile. These
kind of versatile slot guys now are kind
of in vogue in the National Football
League. But how much do you think about
the the fact that he didn't test, he
doesn't have the elite traits, he's a
safety, and then you're picking five.
So, how do you put all that together?
He's one of my top players, but how much
do you take those other things into
consideration? Well, the the testing
thing Here's Here's Here's what I'll
tell you, John, and this is really for
me, you,
and [snorts] let's call it the viewing
public moving forward. A lot of these
guys aren't going to test anymore moving
forward, right? They These players, I
think they realize their power
or the power that they have in a way
that our generation didn't. Our
generation, we showed up at the combine,
we did whatever,
you know, they told us to do. And if you
weren't comfortable running your 40, you
lied and said, "Hey, I tweaked my
hamstring training."
Right? Or you know, you came up with
something. Um but these guys now will
just flat out tell you, "I'm not
running."
That's just is what it is. I think you
look at Marvin Harrison Jr., he didn't
do a single thing Nope. throughout his
and still went top five, right?
Um
Again, I don't think any of these guys
going to run. Travis Hunter didn't run
last year. Yep. Um but I think for a guy
like Caleb Downs, I think he has so much
great tape
on um that you can go back and view. I
don't I don't think I don't think
there's anybody out there that believes
Caleb Downs Downs was going to run a
4-3, right? I don't think anybody
believed that. I think at best you
probably thought he would be in the
4-4-6 range. Um I always said 4-4-8 to
probably 4-5-1. Yeah, I agree.
>> Uh which which for a safety would be is
plenty fast. But what I've always loved
about him I mean, you you go all the way
back to his freshman year at Alabama. He
led Alabama in tackles as a true
freshman.
Like name the last person that's done
that. And then he went and had the
impact he's had at Ohio State. Um
And then specifically this last year, he
plays in a NFL style defense where he's
asked to do a lot. There was a lot on
his plate from a multi-alignment
situation to
him being the primary communicator, you
know, back there. You mentioned that uh
that nickel safety hybrid role, and he
did such a great job at it. Again, and
also playing in the post, and also being
a great tackler. Um I know this this
whole positional value thing,
right? And I I
If he's [snorts] one of your top
football players on your board, and
no matter where you're sitting, if you
know this guy's going to be a Pro Bowl
player,
why not take him?
Right? Because if you don't take him
now, then guess what? Four years from
now, five years from now, if he chooses
if the other team if they get to an
impasse where they can't get a contract
done, then you're going to be paying him
$25 million a year
to get him in your building, right?
Which is which is to me saying you made
a mistake the first time anyway and
passed up on him.
So, I think there are Like you said
before leading into all of this,
there are outliers.
And there are certain guys that you say,
"Well, this guy's different." And the
reason why I think he's a
difference-maker is not only on the
field, but I think he's a culture
changer
you know, in your locker room.
I was uh fortunate enough this summer uh
to attend uh David Mulugheta's uh Elite
Week that he has for all his clients.
And
it was a ton of high school kids there,
was college kids there, was NFL guys
there, and Caleb Downs was one of them.
And I had the opportunity to watch him
work out and be amongst pros and uh see
how he handled his himself.
He was a consummate pro that entire
weekend and I walked away impressed, you
know, with him even more.
Would you put Sonny Styles into that
same group as as a character guy, a guy
that can help change a defense as a
middle linebacker? Talk about a guy like
that does meet all the thresholds and
checks all the boxes on traits and
testing. He certainly does that. The
tape was very good. Would you put Styles
into that same type of category, Ran,
when you evaluate these defenders at the
top of the class?
No, I definitely [snorts] would and just
in terms of just who he is off the
field.
Uh [snorts] met him at the combine,
interviewed him for CBS Sports and you
immediately walk away like
damn, if this kid doesn't make it as a
football player, like I can see him in
the corporate boardroom. Yeah. You know,
in just the way he carried himself and
um love that about him.
I think the Sonny Styles thing is
interesting because I think uh I think
there's a ton of upside there. This is
only his second year playing, you know,
uh playing linebacker after moving down
from safety. So, I think I think he is
one of the guys where that where the
arrow is still pointing up. I think his
best ball is still
uh ahead of him because I did see a
significant jump from 2024 to 2025. 2024
I saw a guy that was hesitant um that
didn't necessarily always knew what he
was seeing. And even from his block
destruction standpoint, it was, you
know, he he look he was more willing to
out athlete the block and what I mean by
out athlete the block was not
necessarily
use that, you know, very good arm length
for that he that he had to create the
separation from the blocks. Everything
was running under the block or trying to
beat the block to a certain point where
we know at this level these guys are I
tell all the young guys that I talk to,
I'm like, "Hey, you're going against
grown men who are married and with
mortgages." Like they're not going to
let you young boys come in and make them
look foolish. And so, these guys
understand angles, they understand their
scheme and they set you up one move
ahead, two plays ahead. And so, um
I think from a human standpoint he
belongs in that category.
Um I think again, depending on where you
see his upside and your fit and I can
see him going as high as four to the
Titans, Sonny Styles. Uh I know Robert
Saleh
was enamored with Tremaine Edmunds, who
you guys just signed, uh him coming out.
I believe that year we had pick nine.
Um and I know that, you know, if if if
Robert Saleh could have had his way,
probably likely would have taken
Tremaine Edmunds at nine. So, now that
he does have his way, you have a similar
style player that can do a lot of the
things in that defense that
you need [snorts] out of the middle
linebacker position that I don't think
the Titans currently have or, you know,
the in terms of they have a great young
tackler in Cedric Gray,
but
being able to carry that deep crossing
route, to turn run, use your height,
your length to affect that throwing
window for the quarterback. They just
don't have that right now. Um so, I can
see Sonny Styles going as high as four,
uh possibly to the Titans. Yeah, a a guy
that can do Fred Warner type things. Not
that he's Fred Warner, but the guy that
can do Fred
>> and I will say, John, it was funny
because
um
I think Tremaine and I'm I'm, you know,
I'm just trying to go back in my mental
rolodex, but I think Tremaine might have
been
one of the top guys or on the board in
terms of the linebacker position and
like I said, if coach Saleh probably
could have had his way, probably
would have liked Tremaine at nine. But
then, in the third round of that same
draft class, he got his consolation
prize, which was Fred Warner, which Not
a bad consolation prize.
>> Right. I always give, but I do always
give coach Saleh and DeMeco Ryans the
full credit when it comes to Fred Warner
and his development because Fred had
never played in the box in college. He
played kind of a big nickel, kind of
detached from the formation.
But the moment we brought him in on a
visit, they were like, "This guy can
play Mike. He could be our Mike." And lo
and behold,
end up drafting a a Hall of Famer in the
third round. Given everyone else that
you know is on the board and who might
be available, who else would you have in
consideration, Ran, for the Giants at
five, given Harbaugh, [snorts] the
coaches, where the franchise is, needs,
all that stuff? Who else would you be
thinking about at five if if you were
running the Giants? Right. So, I think
in recent years, and I had to deal with
this,
um
what, my second year, right? We were
pick six. Were we pick six? Uh yeah, we
were pick six cuz I think the Giants
were Where did they take Malik Nabers?
Was it four?
Oh, boy.
Yes, I think that's correct. I will
double-check that. Yeah, so I think I
think
>> Um
Was it?
Because I know it went in order. It went
Malik Nabers and then it went
>> Six. Nabers was six.
Nabers was six. So, what pick did we
have? Oh, yeah, so we had seven in that
year. So, it was five, six, seven.
Chargers had five, Giants went six, and
then the Titans we were seven. And so,
we were sitting there and we had a clump
of guys and we were like,
in any form or fashion, Joe Alt, Malik
Nabers, JC Latham,
if one of those three are there for us
at seven, that's who we're taking. And
so, I look at this year's draft class
kind of being similar for the Giants.
Obviously, like we talked about,
the draft starts at two. Um
I think the
I think the Jets, of all things, the
Jets kind of hold cards for the Giants.
Right? So, there've been talks about I
think the I think the Jets pick is going
to come down to
um
Arvell Reese and David Bailey.
Is what I think it'll come down to.
>> Um
And then,
so I let's just assume the Jets take
David Bailey
at two. And then so, now it becomes
the Jets, I mean, excuse me, the the
Cardinals.
Now, you're sitting there at three and I
think they'll be choosing between uh
Siaki Ika
from the University of Miami
and Arvell Reese.
Right? I think they'll be deciding
between those two and then the Titans
are sitting there at four. Uh
conventional wisdom says they want an
edge guy. I know a lot of the mock
drafts in recent times say uh
the running back Jeremiah Love uh will
be available to them there at four. Um
Just don't know that they'll do that.
And so, I think, you know, again, Sonny
Styles will come into to fold there and
then there is the the Giants at five.
So, I think some combination
for me, um
let's call it Arvell Reese, let's call
it Siaki Ika,
and let's call it Jeremiah Love.
Right? It's it's some form of those
three will be there. Um
Within that top five, I think that's who
the Giants will be choosing from and
then I think that next tier, which it's
hard to say a next tier in the top five,
but I think that would be the the ideal
three. And then I think after that, I
think some version of possibly Sonny
Styles
or Caleb Downs um
will be there based off of who who's the
best available. The
unfortunate part for a guy like David
Bailey, you can't go back-to-back
with
uh with another edge rusher in the top
five again, knowing that you still have
Kayvon Thibodeaux on your roster. That's
more of a luxury pick, you know, I would
think with with David Bailey.
Uh but Arvell Reese is intriguing to me
because
I view him more as a off-ball
linebacker. So do I.
>> [laughter]
>> And um
and I know he's he's told me
specifically that if he's playing in a
3-4 defense, which would be the base
defense of the Giants,
that he wants to play outside
linebacker. And I understand that, but I
think that's more so him forecasting the
second contract.
And [laughter] he's a smart agent.
Right. That outside linebackers get paid
more than inside linebackers, but I
think to maximize his ability, I think
you play him off-ball on base downs and
I think in those sub packages, kind of
how you guys used Abdul Carter
something. You walk him around, put him
in that spinner type role.
And you can get in your NASCAR package,
right? And have, you know, Thibodeaux
[snorts] and Burns on the outside and
then you walk Abdul Carter and
and Arvell Reese over guards and then
you let those guys work the guards. And
so, um you know, I think it'll be I
think that'll be that next tier. Forever
and a day it always had Carnell Tate
comped uh at number five uh for the
Giants. I think as we go throughout the
process, I don't know that that will
factor in um because again, you took uh
and I posed this question uh to
uh my co-host Ryan Wilson on air.
I was like, "Would you take Malik Nabers
or Carnell Tate?" Oh, it's not even
close. Right. And so, that that's kind
of my point, you know, like you're
taking another receiver in the top five
and
there's such a gap between who they are
as players. You know, Malik is a
legitimate number one wide receiver.
Like that's that's never been a
question. So,
um I don't know that Carnell Tate will
factor in anymore at five. If you want
to know how to manage two minutes of
crunch time football, I'm your man. But
if you're wondering about a long-term
financial plan, you should talk to
Citizens. Hey, I can also talk lawn
care. I'd like to learn about a mowing
routine. Yes, I knew I could help.
Make sense of your money with Citizens.
All right, the two guys I want to ask
you about on follow-ups, and I
appreciate you taking the time this
morning, Ran. Uh Francis Mauigoa, you
mentioned. How do you view him? I mean,
the Giants just re-signed Evan Neal.
Could you start him in at guard and then
maybe plan to move him back out to
tackle once Evan Neal's gone? Do you
view him as a Joe Alt-level tackle
prospect? And then, one guy you didn't
mention is is is Delane, who I think his
tape is phenomenal.
To pick a corner in the top five, I like
him to be a little bit longer. Just my
personal preference.
Do you view those guys as as part of
that elite tier in this in in in this
class?
Well, the thing is with with CC Mawoa,
all fall I had him as my number one
guard.
Like that's where I had him on my board.
I had him as my number one guard.
And a lot of it would too, I I
don't just look at your measurables,
right? Like 6'5, you know, 320 pounds.
Like I wouldn't just look at that.
>> a guard to me on tape. That's how he
moves, at least to me.
>> but here's the thing. And so, like I
look at your body structure.
Right? Like what is your body structure?
Um
if you look at
Peter Skoronski when we drafted him at
11, Peter was 6'4. I think he was 320
pounds. But you looked at Peter's body
structure and it looked like a guard.
Like I think Trent Williams is 6'4.
And he's 320 pounds coming out, but you
look at Trent's body structure and he's
built angularly built like a tackle.
Right? And so, I look at that. And I
remember seeing um
>> [snorts]
>> CC Mawoa at the 2025 pro day just
walking around and I was like, oh, he
kind of looks like a guard.
Like walking around now, seeing him at
the pro day this past week
like he looks like a tackle. His body
looks really good cuz I and he wanted to
show off. So, he had his shirt off
you know, and and he
you know, he looked good. Um but I what
for what it did was even prior to the
pro day
I went back and I watched a lot of the
playoff tape. Playing him watching him
have to block elite pass rushers
on the edge at tackle. And to your
point, I wasn't so sure that he had the
the initial quickness off the line in
his pass set. But here's what I learned.
He makes it look so easy
that we don't take that as he has the
quickness and the twitch in his body. If
you can get your hands on the film,
John, of that pro day, you watch him. It
was one specific drill where
they drop a tennis ball and he has to
come out pull. He's running full speed
and he has to dip and scoop underhand
scoop the tennis ball off the ground and
still move. Like it was flawless. His
ability to
bend [snorts] at the way not just be a
waist bender and come over forward, but
to be able to bend his knees, scoop it.
He looked like a pass rusher running the
hoop being able to dip and get that low.
And so, I think he could play tackle.
I asked him. I interviewed him after the
pro day and asked him
where have teams [snorts] talked to him.
Do they talk to him about guard, but
talk to him about tackle? And he was
like, listen, I just want to be one of
the starting five.
I don't care if it's guard. I don't care
if it's tackle. Do I believe I can play
tackle? Yeah.
But I want to be a starter. And I want
to be one of the starting five. And so,
for me
>> [snorts]
>> what made me ultimately move him back to
tackle is because and make him the
number one tackle
is because I think you're getting a
starting tackle and a starting guard.
And I think no matter how you shake it
you know, you have Al Woods back and you
get him and you say, hey, this is the
succession plan. Right? There've been a
lot of great offensive tackles and some
guys have gone on to be Hall of Famers.
I think Jonathan Ogden started his first
year at guard for the Baltimore Ravens.
Um there've been a ton of guys that have
come through that started their careers
at guard, ultimately kick out at tackle
and have long productive careers. And I
see the same for CC Mawoa.
Do you think Delane would match what
Denard Wilson's looking as a corner? Do
you think he's not quite long enough for
that? No, I think he does. I think he
100% does he fits there. But I just
think right now, I think top five is a
little too rich to take take corner.
And I say and and again, I'm a big
Mansour Delane fan.
I remember him jumping off the tape very
early that Clemson game week one. I
think he had, you know, anywhere from
three to five pass breakups that game. I
think he really established himself. But
for me personally coming into the year
I had Jamar McCoy from Tennessee as my
number one corner. And I thought if
Jamar McCoy had worked out at the
combine and put up some impressive
numbers, I thought he could have
reestablished himself as the number one
corner in the draft. And that's why
specifically for Mansour Delane
I don't know that you go top five there.
You know, because I think I think if all
things were equal
and
I don't know if
>> [snorts]
>> if McCoy's just not healthy or the
advice that he's getting from his team
and those around him to not do anything
thus far um
you know, I think that hurt. And I
believe someone texted me the other day
that Mansour Delane ran in the 4-3s
you know, at his pro day, which I think
that was a question people question
whether he had the speed. Um but again,
I say that if Jamar McCoy had worked out
at the combine and he didn't necessarily
have to run 4-3s, but had he worked out
at the combine and showed, you know, the
movement skills that you saw on tape
because I think he probably has the best
ball skills
you know, in this class at the corner
position. Had he worked out and showed
those same movement skills and ran well,
I think he could have easily established
himself as the top corner in this class.
All right, last two questions, Ran. I
appreciate all the time you're giving us
this morning. You mentioned Jeremiah
Love briefly.
How much would you consider him at five
if you're the Giants? You have two young
running backs on rookie contracts that I
think if you're the Giants, you like.
Love obviously would be an upgrade
there.
But there are other spots that maybe you
could use bigger upgrades. You know, you
can find the top running back in free
agency. You know, Kenneth Walker made
what, $15 million a year this year? You
can find those guys if you need them.
How much would you consider Love here if
you're the Giants and you're John
Harbaugh and Joe Schoen trying to
reshape this roster in the coaches'
image? No, I think you I think he
definitely needs to be considered. And
again, and I'm glad you said what you
said, like you can find them in free
agency. It goes back to what I was
saying if you pass on him now and then
four years from now, you have to go pay
him let's call it 17, 18, 19 million
dollars a year like when you could have
drafted him and at least got five years
out of him and possibly a six year with
a franchise tag, like to me that defeats
the purpose. I think he is a bell cow
runner. I think you you can turn around,
give him the load.
I think he
>> [snorts]
>> he would take a lot off of Jackson
Dart's plate. He could catch the ball
out of the backfield. Um I think he is
head and shoulders There's probably I'll
say it this way.
From him to the number two person is
probably the biggest gap of every
position in this draft class. And I
think that um
you can't always assume that I'm a
running back, so I get defensive when
people say, oh, you can find those guys,
right?
>> Of course.
But I I also think, yeah, you can find
productive players. Like I mean, we saw
the Giants, they took Skat where they
took him took Tyrone Tracy where they
took him and have gotten solid
production out of them. But let's be
real. And I know this is a sore, so you
know, Giants fans excuse me cuz Giants
fans have been on my ass all year
because I gave Jackson Dart a C plus.
You know what I mean? But whatever. Um
I don't think any of those guys, whether
it's Cam Skat or Tyrone Tracy, I don't
think those guys have given the Giants
Saquon Barkley production. No,
absolutely not. That's fair.
>> You know what I mean? And I And so, I I
I say that to say and I'm not saying cuz
I don't think Jeremiah Love is Saquon
Barkley. I think Saquon Barkley,
I think Bijan Robinson, I think I think
they those guys were unicorns. Right?
>> [snorts]
>> And but I do think that Jeremiah Love is
a is a good back that can that can be
what the Giants need. Um more so than
the way that Cam Skat
and Tyrone Tracy. I think
you know, I think Skat
and and Jeremiah Love will give you
that, you know, proverbial thunder and
lightning. Right? Because I think with
Skat, you got to protect him from
himself. You know, he only, you know,
knows one way to run and we both know
that that will lead to a shorter career
um in the league, you know, running like
that. And uh
>> [snorts]
>> you know, I don't think either one of
those guys will be second contract guys
and that you're paying for, you know,
for the long haul in terms of the two
that are currently on the roster. So, I
think Jeremiah Love should definitely be
in that conversation at five. But I
think if it comes down to it and
you know, Ar'vell Reese is there or CC
Mawoa is there, I think you're getting a
comparable player at a bigger need than
you would be at the running back spot.
I'm with you on that. All right, final
one here, Ran. 37, you mentioned from 22
to 50, these guys are all kind of the
same, right? So, where do you think
you're going to find kind of like one of
the thickest positions where you think
the Giants could find some value for
what they need at 37? I think 37 would
be, you know, let's just let's just call
it let's just say Ar'vell Reese is not
on the board and you go Mawoa.
I think 37 would be the spot where you
would look at the receiver or the inside
linebacker. Again, I think Chris
Braswell is worth the conversation there
at 37. I think a guy like Jacob
Rodriguez out of Texas Tech is worth the
conversation.
>> Um you know, at 37 as inside linebacker.
Um
so, I [snorts] think that's where
I think perfect world for the Giants
probably right now, if you want to
maximize the board, I think Mawoa at
five
will solve
a current a current problem, but a
future problem as well. All right? So,
you get you a guard. You get you a
player that could be your guard this
year, but then kick out the tackle in in
the coming years.
But then again, you're sitting there at
37 and you have the opportunity to
get a Chris Brazil
trying to look at the the makeup so you
sign Darnell Mooney you sign Calvin
Austin the third you still got Darius
Slayton there who is ironically enough I
know you know my dad but my dad and
Darius Slayton's dad graduated high
school together and I
yeah so they're best friends
>> [snorts]
>> so
uh
and so you have Darius Slayton obviously
Malik neighbors is coming back I don't
think a guy like Casey conception
you know cuz to me now you're getting
smaller and smaller
in your in your wire receiver room so a
guy like Chris Brazil
maybe a Omar Cooper Jr if he's there
depending on you know the style of wire
receivers that you're looking for
but again
a Jacob Rodriguez type guy
at that inside linebacker spot where I
think would be a really good fit I mean
let's see how the how it all shapes out
what if
and I don't see Peter Woods falling all
the way down to 37 but that's a
conversation of Peter Woods is available
at 37 it's a conversation of Caleb Banks
from Florida is available to you at 37
so you just got to play them cuz all
those spots are indeed
indeed needs for for the Giants as well
as safety what if Emmanuel mcdougall
Warren is available to you at 37 a true
ball Hawk a guy that can go get it a
Colton hood in this in the second round
out of Tennessee so I think at 37
they'll have their their plethora of
picks but I think in a perfect world
let's call it CC malinoa
at five and a Jacob Rodriguez or a Chris
Brazil at 37 and you mentioned Dart very
quickly you don't you don't have to talk
about your grade where do you think he
needs to take the next step right to to
start to become that franchise guy based
on what you saw off his rookie tape
listen I mean and I want to go back and
defend myself
and my C plus right I think there's a
lot of us in this world that are we turn
they turn their nose up at a C plus but
there's a lot of us C plus people
walking around
this Earth right now
you know what I mean so C plus is a is a
very passing grade I think the next step
for Jackson Dart is
just seeing the field better
in terms of his passing ability I
thought it got to a point at the earlier
part
that if number one was open he he would
hit number one but I think if number one
wasn't open before he got to his second
window he would kind of peek at the rush
a little bit right and then I think that
kind of allowed him to flee the pocket
prematurely sometimes so seeing the
field a little bit better but you can
say that about all rookie quarterbacks
right because that's a part of their
maturation they're going against these
tough defenses one thing I can tell you
right now is that OTAs will be hell for
him cuz Denard is going to throw
everything at him
so [snorts] he can prepare for that
which will make him better you know come
fall but then the other part two and I
think
I think everybody would agree on this
he's got to protect himself better know
when to give his body up for a first
down or a touchdown versus when to live
to see the next down get his pass down
slide or get the ball out of bounds and
so I think he'll ultimately be fine I
know Brian Callahan is going to coach
him you know very hard but very well and
the cool thing for him having a Brian
Callahan is the level of communication
that he's going to be able to have to
you know let Kelly know what he likes
what he doesn't like in terms of the
calls and which will help put him in the
most successful spot
Ryan tell the folks where they can find
everything you're up to right now
I mean you can come check us out on with
the first pick podcast myself and Ryan
Wilson
I'm mainly on CBS Sports I do some hits
with my man Bruce Murray on SiriusXM
radio we come on on Mondays I guess it's
12 to 3 Eastern Standard Time so you
catch me on all those platforms
Giants fans leave me alone please
>> [laughter]
>> like you guys like tore me a new one you
should have showed me some love I come
from the Giants tree like I'm a a baby
giant
please can we be friends can we just hug
it out and just be friends please I
think Giants fans will be in a much
better mood around this time next year
hopefully if if everything goes well
Ryan I apologize I did not mean to keep
you this long but you get
>> no man this is fun you know I you you
know you know I love talking ball and
you know anytime you call when you said
hey let's do it again I was like let's
let's figure out a time let's get it
done you're the man you just kept
throwing gold at me great information
that's all the time we have in the
Giants little podcast brought to you by
Citizens official bank of the Giants we
will see you next time everybody
>> [music]